hello and welcome it's September 30th
2024 we're in active inference guest
stream
89.1 generic framework for a coherent
integration of experience and exposure
rating and reinsurance with Stefan berer
and also joined by Rolan bori so thank
you both for joining Stefan to you for a
presentation we'll look forward to that
and the
discussion okay thank you Daniel welcome
everyone
um let me quickly give an overview of
what I'm going to present it's about re
insurance and
reinsurance maybe some of the people on
the call are familiar with what re
insurance is if you are not no problem
I'm going to explain everything you need
to know basic what insurance reur do
they provide coverage to insurance
companies and when they provide a
contract to cover the risk they of
course need somehow to rate this risk
and there's two different approaches
which are traditionally used one is
experience rating the other exposure
rating and what I'm to present the new
framework which is integrating the two
into one
um integrated framework basically and
just to what you can see what is
highlighted there are three comp
components to it the first component is
a generative
model the second is I mean the
generative model he will create a
artificial or simulated
claims and what we need to do before we
can do an analysis we need somehow to
reduce these high dimensional complex
objects into some uh smaller number of
what I call reduced random variables and
then useing basent inform
to basically calibrate the model this is
basically what it's supposed to do so
and what you see on the bottom I made a
reference to some people in the history
so the
traditional approach where you use a
experience rating you're taking the
claims from the past you somehow project
this into the future and use this data
as a model for the future claims
activity so that's why I put there
Kepler who basically took the data from
T bra and then he derived his laws for
the motion of the planets and then
contrast is Newton which basic can
derive these laws by some much more
fundamental principles so basic in one
case you you model the date and the
other case you model the world so this
is the difference between the two of
course in biology would have the Aristo
on one hand side and then
um uh Darin on the other other side and
from the statistics what you see on the
left side this is the father of the
classical statistics of Fisher and on
the other side to put the base so this
is where the frame where we are
operating now to my talk I will first
give some background information and
explain why this is
relevant then I will somehow make a link
to active inference then also point out
to some of the challenges which we are
facing in this uh attempt and then I'll
provide with a road map for a solution
and then I will show some examples and
just for your information I will not
show any formulas here so whenever you
want to look into the formulas we can go
back to the paper you find all the
technical details so I'll just
describe um with the help of numbers and
some charts or some graphics what I'm
going to or the basic ideas are so just
if you expect any formulas you will be
disappointed
okay so
first um what I've done I've taken some
real numbers from a reinsurance company
and this is
ss3 and from ss3 I've taken not the
whole business but just one segment
which is the PNC reinsurance which is uh
property casualty and Specialty
lines um two other segments which this
three has is uh corporate solution so
this is the dire Direct Insurance
provided to large corporations and there
is also life and health so what I'm Pro
showing here is only PNC reinsurance re
contracts with insurance
companies and swiss has developed about
20 or not 25 years ago an internal
framework for economic valuation of the
business and it has started in 2013 to
publish the numbers so evm results which
is an economic valuation of the business
contrast to the traditional Financial
numbers which have been published and
what is relevant for us here I'm not
going to into details of evm but what we
have is so-called present values of
future cash flows this is the basis for
it and then it's um the analysis is done
by underwriting year and not by
Financial year so these are the two main
um the most important elements of evm
and what we have is let's say the gross
premiums and then commissions and the
commissions are the amount of the
premiums which goes to the
intermediaries so Brokers and or goes
back to the insurance company in the
form of a contribution to the claim H to
the internal expenses so what matters is
what they've shown here as net premiums
so this is it has been increasing for
about from 13 billion in 2013 to roughly
18 billion in 20 uh 23
and on the right you see the mean and
then I use the the mean over the of the
net premiums as a base so this is 100%
And then you can see what happens to
these premiums so the more the largest
part of it is used to pay claims so this
is about
85% then you have about 10% is the
internal the expenses of the reinsure of
swisser then we have some other elements
like taxes taxes depend on the on the
profit so it's linked to the bottom line
then we have U Capital cost Capital cost
is linked to the risk but these are
relatively small numbers and then the
finance people have introduced some
small details which they put on other so
there is a lot of work going into these
small elements but what is really matter
what really matters for the success of
the company is what we have here in
claims and benefits and how much premium
we the company earns to cover these
claims and just as a what we see here is
the
numbers um published at time one so one
year after Inception so the 2013 numbers
are published in
2014 based on the information which is
available at that point in time but
claims they have a relatively long
um they take a long can take quite some
time until they are known and paid and
reported so there is only little
information available after one year so
there is some um development taking
place later and all the developments of
Prior years is shown at the very bottom
and we can now see two important things
one is if you go here to the evm reals
you see kind of a cycle so there is some
positive results then it becomes very
negative for a couple of years and then
it becomes positive again so this is one
thing this is the nature of the business
and the cycle has two components one the
premium rates go up and down and second
also the terms and conditions of the
policies they might be tighter or uh
they might be released so there's also
the claims might change during the
during the cycle but what is what we see
here is the bottom line result and then
there is another element here the evm
profit the evm profit of pre pre prior
year
and here we can see some quite negative
numbers and then here again this is
something which uh you want to avoid
this is the big surprise which at the
time of underwriting you put aside a
certain amount of the premium for the as
reserves for the claims and then it
turns out that this is not sufficient
and then you have
to uh find some means or take Capital to
increase the reserves in later years and
this is basically what what reur wants
to
avoid so of course the what is not shown
here is the the initial assessment of
the underwriters at the time when they
look at the business so they also have
an estimate for the claims this will be
the claims at time zero this is are the
initial reserves what we see here is
claims at time
one um and what is important to know of
course the estimate is quite on a
contract or a transaction level is quite
High the
uncertainty but the problem is that
underwriting functions they tend to
underestimate the claims during the soft
market so they're too optimistic and
then they adverse developments and they
overestimate the claims cost during the
heart market so they're may be too
conservative and then might miss some
opportunities and if you just look at
this picture here here then you can say
there is a potential for improvement in
this case of CIS I mean this is my from
the outside you maybe the internal
people will say something different but
just looking at these numbers I would
say the adverse development so the
numbers which you have here which in the
order of 1 to two billion this could be
improved potentially by about 10age
points of the premiums so about let's
say one or two billion per year so there
is quite some potential to reduce this
uncertainty that's one motivation to do
this and the second motivation is of
course by better risk selection you
could also increase the bottom line
results so this 470 million the average
but let's say one which is 3% maybe put
one or two percentage points of the
premium volume so these are is the
motivation so we talk about quite
substantial numbers in the case of the
profit maybe 100 or 200 million per year
which additional profit could be done
but better this collection and it comes
to adverse development which is
basically
The Unwanted uh development in future
years maybe one or two billion this is
my claim people can prove me wrong but
this is what I think is
possible now sorry now if you look at
this slide there is three uh charts the
temporal development and what we have
I've done here I've taken the numbers by
subline of business this so this also
published by SS I'm not inventing
anything and let's first look on the
left hand side what we see here is
different lines of business so the red
one here will be um liability on the top
we have here property and we see they
develop quite differently now what is
this development which I'm showing here
this chart shows which percentage of the
CL claims is reported after one year and
we see in casualty it's only about 10%
in property it's maybe
50% and then it takes maybe in casualty
10 years maybe or even longer until all
the claims have been reported so this
just a reporting pattern and which is
lined bu dependent then reported means
that there is a an initi the insurance
company they have notified the insur
there is this this this claim and we
have put up some case reserves and
reserves for this but then it can take
another uh couple of years until the
claims are paid and this payment pattern
is show here on the right hand side so
you see again here in the case of
liability it's very slow so the payments
can can take 10 20 30 years in the case
of short tail or property this is
normally settled within a few years
and then what I have shown in the middle
this is the key topic of today so one
point is the initial estimate of the
claims so this is what underwriting is
doing and the question is what is
happening with this estimate down the
road and this is shown here in the
middle and here in the for the
red which is liability again you can see
here at time one it's only a to
depending 70
80% of the latest numbers so there is in
time one the reserves are maybe here 80
or 70% and then these reserves have to
be gradually increased until they reach
a stable level in the case of property
or xent lse at time one we are higher
and then it decreases so here we have
kind of a favorable development so
reserves can be released and here we
have an adverse development which means
you have to constantly increase the
reserves in order to be able to pay the
all the claims and if we go back here we
can see in the first after one year it's
only 10% of the claims have been
reported so whatever reserves we have
here is the estimate of the underwriters
there is nothing else no other
information so here we can be very
confident that the initial estimate of
the underr was more or less on the same
level because there's no additional
information coming in so they start
10 to 30 or 20 to 30 percentage points
below the ultimate which is quite
substantial in the case of short tail
lines it's not so clear because you see
here about 50% of the claims have
already been reported so it could be
that the claims manag they're quite
conservative at the beginning they
Reserve more than what is necessary and
then it comes down here we don't know we
maybe we started higher it came down
maybe started below and it came up in
the first year it's not so clear here
but overall we can say some business
starts to high which have a and then it
has a favorable development some starts
just at the right level and it's
flat or you have an adequate estimate at
the beginning and in other cases it's
adverse and this is basically what we
want to
avoid now there is another
complication and this is that the market
is not stable there Market is goes
through cycle as we have seen at the
beginning with the numbers of Swiss R
and what I'm trying to show here is if
you take each and every contract you can
put a tag on each one and say it either
contributes to the economic profit or
it's just adequate to cover the expenses
and all the costs or maybe some business
you even if it is negative but you want
to keep it because you want to keep the
client relationship so this then and the
the problem is nobody knows what the
true color is so basically the
underwriters they take each contract and
they do an assessment and they say one
contract is green one is Amber one is
red but it could be POS false positives
or false negatives this is not known and
of course if a contract is red and you
say it's green then you write as much as
possible of it and then you end up
having this adverse an adverse
development
and of course you also then you have the
winner scur so you're much much more
likely to get this contract than having
one which is positive and everyone else
also sees it positive so this is kind of
the um broader context in which the
underwriting or the market is
operating
and if you say the underwriters are
biased and you can say they um are so
there is a true let's say that the true
border between the three B buckets but
the underwriters they believe that the
border is may be up
here um in the case of a hard market so
they are too conservative they say some
business which actually is already Amber
they put it into the red bucket and some
business which is Amber they would put
it uh which is green they would put it
into the Amber bucket and why is ver
during the soft market so this is the
problematic and by improving
the uh underwriting and by avoiding the
bias and minimi or reducing the
uncertainty you can get this dash line
here closer to the true border and here
as well so that's the aim of the whole
thing so this is where I'm making a
claim that there is a quite some
potential for
improvement um for reinsurance company
now there is of course also different
approach in reinsurance so if you're a
big company like ssy then you have to do
this
Assessments in other cases if you are a
small you say I don't do this myself I
save this cost and I just follow the
leaders yeah then you just basically can
do it for free and you try to write the
same business as the large ones and then
you have it the same at the lower cost
ratio this is also a possible approach
or you can say I don't care over the
cycle the market will correct itself and
I just write and that I'm sure that I
can survive the sof market and then I
will earn during the heart Market that's
also a possible approach so we talk here
about a company which does a fundamental
assessment and that's why it's necessary
to go through this
analysis okay now just a few thoughts
about how to link this to active
inference and what I've course been
thinking about the corporations so they
corporate agents they act very similar
to
humans um I mean there are also
competing for resources they have an
incomplete knowledge of the external
World um they also use the internal
representation of the external
world with the help of models and so on
then we have multiple departments which
in our Corporation and they use of
course they have a different picture of
the outside world and they also have
different part interest so they are not
always pursuing the same the same goal
so this is kind of
maybe we feel the same as humans we are
also not always sure One S wasn't wants
to go in One Direction on the other
direction so I think this is very
similar to
corporations and of course corporations
at the end they have people there at
least this is still the case so we have
also biological brains driving them and
I think active inference is a very good
tool to also understand the behavior of
corporate agents in many different
levels but what I'm doing here I'm just
focusing on underwriting or
inurance
and
um what I'm going to show how gen um
generative models can be used in this
process and maybe just if you want to
look at uh a
broader role of uh active inference so
in the in economics then there is one
link which also introdu the term of
cognitive economics so this is where it
in the broader picture where it would
fit okay now what I'm showing here is
what you need to understand about how re
Insurance works so we have the external
world where we have U objects at risk
this can be buildings this can be people
this can be airplanes this can be
corporations which maybe could default
and so on so these are the objected risk
then we have the range the insurance
company which I call here the sedent
which issues policies to cover some risk
for these objects then there is the
external world where you have the
generative process which creates all
kind of events and some of these events
Like An Earthquake or Windstorm
or an accident or a defaulting company
results in insured
claims now the reinsurer doesn't get all
this information which is available on
the site of the seeden company what the
seeden does it creates a submission and
the submissions you can put it into
three buckets in one bucket we have the
claims which are reported to the
insurers normally this is claims about
for certain
threshold the second bucket contains the
contract terms so of course you have the
uh what were the insurance conditions in
the past but maybe also some insurance
conditions so insured retentions or some
limits and the like so what is which act
like a filter on the claims and the
third bucket is the exposure profile
which is basically some statistics about
sometimes also details about the insured
polities and objects at risk so in the
case of earthquake you maybe want to
know is my the building which I'm
covering um in California on top of
fault or is it somewhere I don't know in
in the center of Africa where there is
no earthquake risk and so there it's
important to have also some additional
information but what exactly we find in
the exposure profile the depends very
much on the line of business the G of
claims this is more much more
standardized basically what you have is
the amount of the claim and the payments
so you can put it into cash flows and
some outstanding claims so this is some
it's much easier to standardize the
claims but in exposure you need specific
information depending on the line of
business then what re insurers then have
they as I mentioned already before you
have two models one is experience rating
the other is exposure rating experience
rate takes the claims and contract terms
the exposure rating takes the exposure
and the contract terms then there is a
quite heavy involvement of the
underwriter or the ACT which is
depending who does it and in both models
you then get some results with some
statistics and since these two results
can be quite different there is some
blending process that keep place and
then you end up with the projective
statistics for the cover year then you
take it into consideration other uh
things like you have of course
underwriting consideration client
management this has some saying and risk
managements and finance so there is now
this information is just one element in
the decision process and at the end of
the day you end up with a reinsurance
contract for the future so this
information is about the past and the
present you and you use it to project
some statistics and the and the
expectations for the future this is
basically where you have the expected
loss cost which I mentioned before and
which you want to be unbi be unbiased
and um as minimized uncertainty so this
is where the circle is closing you could
also represent it with a mark of blanket
you have um some some things happening
inside of the blanket information coming
in and some action going out so this is
where active inference is basically
uh
visualized okay now the step to the
integrated approach and is so basically
we're looking now into these two parts
or these two models The Experience
rating and exposure mate uh model this
is the focus
area and what we do here we have two
things first we have a generative model
now this generative model is very
similar to the exposure rating model but
the difference is the exposure rating is
only applied to the Future to the cover
year while the generative model is
basically taking the same sorry
model and you apply it to the past so
not you don't only apply it for the
cover year this is then comes later but
you first do a a calibration of this
model and this calibration is done with
the report claims so you use the claims
not to project them into the future but
you take the model and project the model
to the past and then you compare the
outcome of your model with the actual
claims and then you calibrate the model
and once it's calibrated you can take
this model projected to the Future and
produce all the statistics you need for
the future cover so this is the basic U
uh secret of this presentation so as I
mentioned before it's a generative model
you have reduced claim statistics and
you have Bas in inference which you
apply to calibrate model maybe you have
to go through multiple C iterations but
this is basically where the maging is
happening and what I have done in my
paper I've basically looked at this part
here because here the generative model
you need to come up with very specific
model for each business segment so for
each line of business you have different
data available you have different models
which you are using so this is where
really the experti of the rer comes into
place so they will have to provide these
exposure models or generative models for
each segment but once this is done then
you can basically standardize this part
here the model has to produce some
claims in a standard format you compare
them with the reported claims and you
then come up with some calibration
parameters which you feed back into your
model and once this is calibrated you
then can then apply to the Future and do
everything you need to do on on the
right hand side that that's basically
the the magic here and we will see it's
much then it's much you need much less
um input from the underwriter because
here in the past when you need to when
you uh do experience right you have to
project these claims to the Future so
there's a lot of assumptions going into
this process because the if you go to
the past the portfolio was different
maybe the claims you had in the past are
no longer representative so there's many
many um assumptions which come from the
underwriter and this can be avoided in
this approach
here okay now so far it sounds
relatively easy but of course if we we
easy maybe it would have been done so
there is some challenges which you need
to um resolve and to understand this
what I've done here and just taking a
few simulated claims and what we have
here is the time
AIS um in the vertical we have the
incurred amount so the estimate of what
the ultimate is going to be and in the
y axis I have the paid amount and let's
assume here at the end it's settled so
you can see the estimate so first it um
goes up and then it comes down and then
there is some adjustments in the end it
goes up again so you can see this in
this curve here the paid first there is
nothing paid and then it goes up and
then eventually we have the final
payment so this is one example but what
can also happen is that at the beginning
you know nothing about the claim so the
claim is reported with some DeLay So it
the accident date is here in 2016 but
the reporting date is
2020 so in this time you have to put up
socalled ibnr are in incurred but not
reported reserves for all the claims
which will be reported later we have
also seen this at the beginning the case
of C the reporting pattern was the chart
on the left so this is the the nature of
the business now if I take one claim so
the whole graph here is one claim and
you can either represent it with a graph
in a threedimensional space as I did
here or you can take each payment and
each incur adjustment and say that's
just one element and then you put it
into a high dimensional space so you can
say the each claim is an element in a
high dimen sample space and the
dimension here is maybe some some
between 10 in the best case or can I go
be up to 100 so it's very high and it's
just High dimensional space where it's
very very sinly populated imagine you
get about maybe 100 or in a uh or 1,000
claims per submission and in a um if you
have a claim with 100 or 50 or even 20
Dimensions you completely lost there's
nothing you can do so what is done here
and this is maybe the only
formal
um um symbols I'm using here I say the
sample space is high dimensional and
what we do with the compos it in M
onedimensional spaces that's basically
the whole idea behind so we need to find
some variables which are more or less
independent and we project these claims
to these uh subspaces and then we can
solve the problem in in a onedimensional
space a couple of times but it's end
with a onedimensional problem which is
much easier of course because then we
have 100 to 1,000 claims in a
onedimensional space and this is easy to
handle so this is the the second part so
the reduction and I will show you how
this is done but just to understand that
this step is necessary else you there's
nothing you can do now if I go here how
can we solve this so this this is again
another representation of the standard
approach so what you have down here you
have claims which are in this case 10
years old so I use minus for relative to
the underwriting year so it's
underwriting year minus 10 here these
claims have been you have a reporting
pattern of 10 years so you know uh the
first 10 years of the
development but for the most recent
years so which is minus one you have
only one year of
development so and this is now if you
try to do traditional experience rating
there is two things you need to do you
need to project all the past to the
Future so this is one step yeah so you
need to Trend the claims and say on as
if basis a claim which happened in the
year minus 10 what would it be if it
would happen in the year plus one which
is basically my cover period and and
then what you see here is you get these
kind of triangles so some claims you
have 10 years of development but the
most recent one you have only one now
the problem is that these recent claims
are may be representative for the
portfolio but they have very little
development the old claims you have a
lot of development but they're no longer
representative and now what you need to
do is you need to take this triangle and
project it to the uh to the end and see
what is the end of these things so
there's a lot of as I said a lot of
underwriting assumptions going into
these to these fundamental steps and
this is the experience- based approach
in the case of exposure rating what you
to take the information which is
available at normally the minus one so
the market experience these are the
market models you have the exposure
profiles Insurance conditions you
project everything to the cover period
and you apply your model and you get an
exposure based uh result and then you
take the two blend them and that's then
the
result um I can take the same now and
represent what is it in the this gen
integrated approach so again the three
steps so first I now use
my exposure model not only for the
future this is then the last step this
is what I will have to do but before I
do this I'm calibrating my model so I
apply
the model to the past so I take all the
market experience which I had in the
past the profiles from the past the the
models which can change over time and
the insurance conditions so I have a one
model for each year some of the
information might be the same but
basically I can now run this model for
the year minus 10 and I can create not
only one but 100 or thousand or as many
as I want simulated sets with
claims um and I do this for the entire
period so I have here now a large number
of
sets let say it's K different sets and I
have one observed set and now I can say
the general statement is my model is
calibrated if the if this one observ
observe set of claims is not an outlier
in the set of all um Sim the claims so
if this is one um element or basically
one um member of this family here then I
can say Yes um I cannot reject my model
because it is compatible with the data
and once this is the case then I can
project it to the Future and um run the
model now on the problem is now doing um
comparison on this level so compare the
all
the claims which have in here with all
the claims have in here we are operating
in this High dimensional space and there
is basically no way to do it so what we
do in a first is we reduce the claims so
this is happening here and we represent
the simulated claims in the same way as
we represent the observed claim so we
use the same statistics so from the
latest year I could of course I could
simulate it till there end but I'm only
taking the first year so the system
knows behind what's happening till the
end but for the analysis I'm only taking
the first year and if I go back 10 years
I take the first 10 years of the
simulation so basic exactly the same
representation of the claims in the
simulated sets and in The observed set
now I projected as I said before to this
um one-dimensional spaces and then I can
do the analysis and I can up with
calibration parameters this is
the um how this basically
works now we can have now a look at the
how do we reduce the claims and I have
shown here two very
simplified developments one is the
reported pattern and the other or the
incurred and then the paid amount the in
the case of the incur is again it takes
a couple of years until the or some time
until the claim is reported so I've here
a reported
LA and then the claim then first uh
estimate of the incurred and then here
there's an adjustment and here again and
then it go this continues into the
future until the claim is closed but of
course this information I don't have so
what I'm taking here is the
latest estimate for the ultimate
this is what I call I for the incurred
uh star for the case simulation for
instance uh on the right hand side I
have then the payment patterns and what
is important to make sure that the
payments are always smaller than the
incur because usually
um
um as there will be this is one of the
boundary conditions in in this
information but we don't really care
about the individual numbers what we do
is we take here an average leg it's
basically the area which have here above
the curve so this gray area here if I
divide it by the amount then I get the
incured leg this is this part here this
is one of these reduced numbers so I'm
not looking at the details I'm just
taking the average leg which I have here
so this is one figure I'm taking
and and then
another statistic I can use is the
number of adjustments which I have S
this is one 2 three that's also one
number I'm using to calibrate so to say
how many adjustments is an insurance
company making for the claims is it
large or is it small so these are the
reduced statistics here so the reporting
lag the um the amount of course the
incurred leg and the number of
adjustments and on the paid side I can
take very similarly the paid amount or
the ratio which is paid I can also take
a uh a paid L and also the number of
payment so these are some of these
reduced random variables which I'm using
for
calibration so I'm simplifying and these
num numbers are considered to be largely
they're not completely independent but
they are largely independent
now here is another um representation of
the of the process um so we again we
have now at the bottom the events which
are leading to insur claims we have the
set with claims and
the the part which is observed this more
or less what the seeding company is
reporting to the
insurer and then we have a set of
reduced claims
on the S other side we have now the
generative model which is creating the K
sets with simulated claims this can be
very detailed there maybe in the first
step you align this claims
representation with the observed claims
and then in the next step we reduce them
and then we take this information here
to come up with
a conditional distribution
functions then you take the obser ations
and you apply base and you end up with
the calibration parameters which you can
feed back into the model so this is the
another representation of this
process and once the model is calibrated
then of course you can go and apply to
the Future and do everything you need to
be able to rate your
business okay now let's look at some
results um
first what I've done here is some very
simple I've used in this case not actual
claims but I've used the simulat
simulator for the generative process and
what I've done here it's a Lo normal
process and I assume there is some Trend
so I go back the years and I have this
the true probability distribution for
each year which is represented in the
vertical axis here this you see here the
probability
and I've drawn one random number for
each year which is shown here with this
uh small
diamonds and what we also have here is
then the projection to the Future so
assuming this trend continues we have
then the this is then the
true in this case uh uh um for the
generative process which simulated but
this is the true distribution in the
future
now here I have my generative model and
you can see my initial model is is flat
so there is no Trend in
there and what I can do in a in a simple
approach simply say okay let me try to
adjust the level so I'm just moving this
model up and down and try to align it
with the data this is done down here so
here we have then the again flat model
but you can see at the beginning it's
too high because the observations are on
the lower side and at the end it's too
high because the observations are on the
higher side so actually there seems to
be some Trend in the
data and which of course reflects the
trend in the underlying model which is
unknown now if I can also do is to say
okay I'm Trend I'm I'm calibrating the
level and the trend and this is what
I've done here in this third picture
here now I have you can see a model
which is increasing over time so this is
the generative model and you can see now
it's well aligned with the data and if I
compare now just the the first two
moments so the mean and the standard
deviation then here I'm quite close to
the true hidden model so this is
basically unknown but this is what I've
put behind the scenes the true model is
83 with a standard devation of 8.3
and here I have 88 with the standard
deviation of 8.8 so it comes pretty
close here my initial model was 60 with
Sigma of six if I calibrate only the
level I end up with 72 and the standard
Sigma of 72
7.2 so you can see if I use this
approach then I can get very close to
the hidden true model here is a second
example which is now a compound model so
I have
a uh simulating the number I take a
negative binomial distribution to
simulate the number of claims and then
the log normal distribution to simulate
the severity of the claims and this is
again shown here and the same
approach um you have
the just calibrate the level and you
calibrate the level and the TR TR and
you get pretty close to the initial
model so just a different process behind
but the principle is the same now here I
have another mod approach where I show
you a little bit more in detail what's
actually happening here I have again a
negative binomial distribution for the
generative process now here the I've
shown the pro U probability
Mass uh function so the probabilities
for each uh
outcome and what you show see here in
the second part is then a log normal fit
to this
distribution
and I could I could do the analysis with
the discrete
distribution which is possible but it's
could be computation a little bit more
uh um challenging but it's doable but
what we can see as long as we we want to
we assume that the observations are in
the high density region of the model so
we can easily replace it by a Fed
distribution which is a much easier to
handle because here can use a
um
um um oh can I find the
ter so the whole Basin analysis
basically much easier if you take a l
normal distribution then compare to a
negative
one now here again done the same now
here what I have the probability
distribution is not the model behind
directly but the
simulated uh model so I have the take my
generative model I'm simulating a large
number of claims and then I take the
empirical distribution as the basis for
my analysis and here again I fit a lock
normal distribution so we're just
fitting the first two moments and then I
do the analysis with this um fitted
distributions what I've also shown here
is then I've aggregated the whole 10
year or what is 12 years here into the
uh into the mean and shown the
distribution of the
mean um and I can use this distribution
to calibrate the level if I want yeah so
the level calibration I can do by using
the annual data but I can say I'm just
looking at this overall distribution and
I calibrate it so this is when you see
here then you see the
observation uh and the calibrated
observation is more or less in the
center of the distribution but still if
I look then at each and every year then
I still have this uh Trend which is
missing so if I calibrating level and
Trend then you can can see here I come
I'm up with a model which is very close
to the initial or to the true hidden
generative process so this is
um the how it works so you take your
generative model to the create a um
simulated distributions you
fit uh discrete dist uh sorry a
continuous distribution to it and then
you apply B
by using your priors and you find out
can find out the calibration
parameters now here what I've now put
everything
into uh one chart to say uh at the end
what we have is we have seen we have
different um reduced random variables so
here is the number of
reported claims then we have the
reported lag and the incurred amount
the incurred lag the number of incurred
adjustments then for the paid we have
the the paid lag and
the um number of payments and what I've
shown on the right is some then
additional have a strongly dependent
variables which are we can use as a to
observe to check if the model is okay
but in this case I've only calibrated
this green area here and here I've just
shown
one uh hand where can change the level
and another one where I can change the
trend and maybe I run multiple iteration
so in this case I think I run it five
times to
basically uh be able to deal with the
dependencies and what I've shown now is
the if you can see here this is now
the the
distribution which I'm using in as a
uh as a prior and then behind this is in
light gray you can see the true
distribution so you see here there's an
offset and after calibration you can see
these two distributions are basically
overlapping which means there is no Gap
anymore and this is here is another big
gap here it's already at the beginning
okay um and so you can see the
calibrated model is basically
very close or the deviation like here is
smaller than one standard deviation so
this is basically as good as you can get
so this is the um how the whole
framework works so you apply to multiple
random variables so the ones I'm
introduced before so the which have
shown here you can have some additional
random variables you which you just
Monitor and then you run your s your
calibration model until you are
satisfied with the result and then you
apply the model to the
Future now just to summarize I've looked
here this also can find in the paper a
comparison so the integrated framework
what are the pluses and the compared to
the standard approach and you can see it
is when you use all information in a
coherent way you don't waste any
information in the standard framework
there's a lot of information you cannot
use and it's not aligned so
it's uh this approach here is Superior
in all regards but there is of course
it's not for free the price you have to
pay is the the computational effort and
Al the effort to set up the whole system
because you need to be able to run it to
the past of course this effort is much
higher but you have the benefit that
maybe you can sub substantially reduce
the uncertainty and the bias in your
estimates so this was the motivation
which we addressed at the beginning
okay here just the summary so basically
we have this the process and the
traditional model and over here
the integrated
approach and it's a kind of a paradigm
shift which requires that you have as a
new mindset to approach it because the
actes especially in certain um in the
angle section region they have well
defined processes is how they are
supposed to rate the and assess their
insurance Bas this is you will not find
in any of these uh um
um documents which are used so it's
completely different approach and this
will the market will probably uh is some
areas maybe not open to it so you need
need you need a different mindset you
need the different skills so I think
once you want to introduce something
like this you need to run this in
parallel to traditional approach until
realize that it has a benefit and maybe
it's a similar process when as when swis
introduced the evm framework it took
about more than 10 years until they went
public with it so these things can take
quite some time but maybe there is the
new uh technology which is around in
artificial intelligence maybe there is
some way to shorten this transition
period okay this is my
part um so thank you for the attention
and as I think we're open for the
discussion and
questions thank you for the great
presentation anyone in the live chat can
write a question otherwise Roland it
would be great for you to say hello give
any remarks in a first question and then
Scott thank you sure so first of all
congratulations Stan so Stefan used to
be my boss at swissy and he's one of The
ogs Who who came up with the uh with all
the pricing Frameworks that are still in
place today and um uh so I'm also I I
was super happy when I met him again and
he he showed me what he's been up to
here and I think that's really where to
take it because when I look back in the
last 20 years or so there were like
almost no developments in this area and
uh I think uh nowadays uh with all the
AI happening it's it's really time to do
something like this but now comes my
biggest question to you Stefan do you
think that the world is ready for this
do you think that anyone will look at
this that there is any any form of
acceptance for
this you see I'm very I mentioned before
I'm very skeptical because we have um
the standardized approaches and I have
already tried also to approach some I
mean left swisser about 10 years ago and
I was doing something completely
different and this then came up somehow
as a side product of other activities
and then I remembered I had this problem
in the back of my mind which I wanted to
already address at that time I presented
some ideas at the time and nobody was
open for it and if I by talking to some
of the former colleagues I have the
impression they are not ready that's why
I mentioned here it requires a new
mindset maybe a new mindset requires new
people and I don't know what has to
happen to the industry maybe there is
some smaller companies which say oh
great this is an opportunity for us so
let's jump on this but I think the old
dinosaurs um so far I don't see any um
willingness to change their
approach okay Scott if you'd like to
give any initial remarks Mar S I know
you wrote a novel in the chat but if
you'd like to give any remarks and maybe
a question somehow
concisely Daniel knows that when I write
a lot in the chat it's excitement so
Stefan uh first of all thank you for
fantastic U presentation and it's a I
feel like first saying where have you
been all my life because you you given
voice to a lot of the things that felt
ever since I've heard about active
inference felt like they
needed to be thought about in risk and
so um I was a a corporate and tax
attorney for 30 years um and so I see
these things and I so my I think my main
question is and one is one of my latter
questions in the chat I'm always looking
for ways to introduce new things where
you don't have to rip and replace
because people who uh remember talking
to the head of security of AT&T one time
and he said why would we do anything
different next Tuesday than we did last
Tuesday when we made a billion dollars
so the so how do how do we get people to
want to do something and what I wonder
is as
a immediate matter could the generative
model the application in your slide
right here under the Beijing approach
the projected generative model to the
Past could that be included as a
calibration in effect but on the
existing projection of claims history to
the Future that analysis is there a way
to make the thing that we're aspiring to
migrate towards a part of an existing
part of the analysis so that it's seen
as being additional but not requiring
migration to the new analysis entirely
is there a way to bolt this on so that
people can start getting used to it
seeing its value in the context of the
analysis that's already being done or or
are they so fundamentally different
that the new approach doesn't lend
itself to being um offered as an add-on
in existing approaches what are your
thoughts on that yeah uh very good
question but if you look at these two
slides just over here yes and over here
both approaches use more or less the
same information of course you might say
okay in here maybe have a different
model than over here but it could also
be the same model so you can I think
it's necessary that in the transition
phase you apply this New Concept in
parallel to the existing uh methodology
so the people can also get the feeling
what is the difference and then it will
take some time I don't know how many
years until you see the results because
you will not see the results immediately
it will take some time until you see
that yes down the road we have really
much less adverse development in the
claims and this you need maybe you need
about 5 years of uh experience until you
see the results really materialize and
this is probably also the time it takes
for the people to familiarize with the
methodology I think if you want to
implement something like this you need
to do it step by step maybe you don't do
it at the beginning for all lines of
business you maybe confine it to a few
lines of business and then over time you
can expand to some other and of course
people need to get used to it and once
so you run the old framework in parallel
and then you can compare and it's time
you get the sense for it and once you
feel um comfortable then you can
basically turn off the old
part thanks again for for all I'll just
G give a short uh note this slide really
captures the difference here going from
extrapolating descriptive statistics on
observables
into making a generative World model
that's based upon or conditioned or
updated from observables but also has
latent States it's like we don't
remember the time series of visual input
and then extrapolate we update based
upon the observations and then use that
to do the now casting and the and the
forecasting so so that has all kinds of
beneficial properties uh the the reduced
represent
uh and the ability to explore direct
counterfactuals generate synthetic data
there's just a lot of things that are
purely time series correlation based
approach doesn't really get at the
question I wanted to throw out to all of
you was as a non reinsurer coming from a
biology perspective what are biological
analogies to the reinsurers or the
underwriters role like could it be be
considered to an epistemic foraging
portfolio like research projects or
could it relate to like
individuals and they're waiting in a
group like Risk profiles of different
foraging strategies within a group or
how how does it happen
because that idea of being uh too or too
little cautious in a changing context
with the hard and the soft market and
there's a TR there's a possibility of of
being over or under risk averse in
either setting but you don't know the
true risk
setting maybe let me try to First keep
Pro Just sh a short thought if I look at
biology then I think biology you find it
over here and I don't have difficulties
to come up with an analogy in biology
which which correspond to this approach
here but maybe someone else has a better
idea but maybe just one with something I
did here it's kind of intentional I put
here let see one part of the information
into red one into green and one into
blue so you could say this corresponds
to the
uh um cones you have in your eyes so
basically you also have three receptors
for different information
which of course it's just now it's not
really one to one comparison but this is
maybe what I tried to do so you have the
receptor you combine this this thing you
come up with the internal um view of the
external world and then you act on it so
this is the analogy as far as I can see
it but maybe someone else has a better
uh example in
mind I mean at the at the broadest level
sorry Roland did you have something no
no just go ahead David I was to say at
the broadest level I put it in the
chat I mean it feels like so I used to
work in
securitizations so you take credit card
portfolios or car um uh Finance
portfolios and put them into packages
and sell them off and I used to occur to
me that what you're doing is trying to
find a bigger sucker uh for the risk
right you package it up you make it look
good and that was the 2008 Financial
break was packages of mortgages they
were crappy mortgages cu the banks were
enthusiastic about selling off the
mortgages so they made the mortgages so
they were appropriate for sale in these
packages but they weren't necessarily
good risk so the risk just got iterated
up and when I'm wondering you you think
about a biology what do what are the
name of the organisms that eat dead
decaying matter like Leaf litter and
stuff like that um whatever they I mean
that the death it's everything's
recycled and risk is recycled
continuously that's what biology is so
you have this big neant Tropic
urge that neg Tropic beings have whether
they're physical or not and they're all
dealing and everyone loses ultimately
their own individual battle on neg
entropy all organisms die but then
they're recycled by other organisms and
so they're coites you know that eat poop
you know things like that I mean there's
all sorts of recycling that happens and
so so it feels like from a reinsurance
perspective you have abstractions of
risk you what you're with with all
Insurance you're creating instruments to
create a a an organism a Sim bio Sim
infogenesis organism that can cause you
to drisk in ways you can't do Alan
period so it's like a UK carot right
you're adding people could just not do
reinsurance and not do insurance and
self-insure and then have to pay the
full price of their house burning down
or whatever but we have these
abstractions where we kind of develop
these eukariotic things and say hey
let's do this together it's a good idea
because then I just pay a premium I get
a house back and then the reinsurers say
hey let's do this together we got all
this different flood kind of risk or
whatever and we can do an evaluation at
a metadata level it feels a lot like
exactly what happens in biology without
memos and voting and all that and so the
power of what you're talking about
revealing Stefan feels like this is how
stuff works if we don't get in our own
way politically and with false models of
from a history of Economics Etc and if
we really allow for the um information
to flow among the entities at risk
doesn't mean that every organism
survives forever it's not about
perpetual motion or Perpetual you know
Perpetual life but rather there's a
balance that happens naturally so so
that feels like as an an immediate
matter there's an ability to sell this
to the quanton Wall Street and say hey
your model is slightly out of whack with
the
biophysical physics reality the
mathematical physical reality and so hey
you're an arbitrager if you want to make
money on the difference between reality
and your model here it is you don't have
to do it do do what you're doing so it
feels like it could be pretty attractive
in the right kind of audience for people
who have to deal with risk
professionally that they can't turn away
once you say something to them if it has
value and shows value they won't be able
to say oh no we're just going to do it
our old way and their clients won't
tolerate that anyway sorry I got a
little excited there it's great great SC
yeah but it's you go you go in the
absolutely correct direction I mean it's
I've I've had to to calibrate a a lot of
risk models in my life and I mean when
you look at the definition of risk it's
what happens above the expected so
normally you subtract the expected and
normally you have to answer questions
like what is the worst that can happen
within a 100 years and uh hardly any one
of us has ever lived 100 years to
actually tell right uh and so um
actually what you learn very quickly
when you're a risk professional is that
you have to break down the question to
something that fits the experience
Horizon of a living being and uh so
typically when I when I was calibrating
risk models uh I saw okay this guy has
been in his profession for 10 years so
um I I was asking questions around what
what was the worst thing that happened
in 10 years and then given a model you
try to extrapolate so what's the worst
that can happen in a 100 years right and
in my opinion this approach here is is
just doing it much more systematically
you know uh so we always had a bit of a
tendency to do this but it it was more
heuristics and and this kind of gives it
a more a more scientific uh way of of of
looking at the
problem that's that's awesome I'll just
make one quick
sorry um I mean you mentioned Scott
mentioned the the CL Financial Market
you know when I joined the re insurance
industry this was many years ago the
first thing which happened was the
collapse of the so-called LMX market and
this was the London excessive loss
Market um and what they did there is
they just handed the risks from one to
the next and it went around the circle
many many times and then there were
claims and the claims were also circled
around so the same claim you had already
sudden you get it by the back door again
you put it on top of it and this
happened until someone run out of cover
and then it w there were some big losses
then happening some interal events some
other things I think there was a piper
Alpha and there was a wind storms in
Europe there were hurricanes on and
suddenly this whole thing collapsed yeah
so it was working before because the the
circling the things around took very
long as long as it was with paper but
then they started to introduce uh new
technology there was time of computers
the first computers so the whole thing
went much faster and the whole thing
collapsed and so the industry had to
learn already in the past and I don't
know what has to happen for the industry
to maybe go through a new uh leap and to
start to implement new uh um approaches
because as long as there is nothing
massive impacting as you also have
mentioned before then maybe people are
just saying okay why should I change
anything everything is okay
and if I if I can the um so I put in the
chat that's a direct relationship of
what you're talking about there to
climate change and let me tell you
what's I think is going on here it's I
think it's pretty pretty wild so we talk
about abstractions we have abstractions
upon abstractions you got Futures
markets and derivatives and they're
trading upon trading upon trading and
there's all intangible now there's a
connection ultimately to some
physicality some commodity or some
phenomenon but they're abstractions that
are layered on abstractions and that's
fine but the challenge is we're trying
to drisk and create neg
entropy we're dissipating information
differentials in those abstract areas
and that requires
energy AI requires coal
burning and so the energy required to
maintain the energy generation in
physical space coal oil Etc um required
and the agriculture required to feed the
people to did all that stuff that's
required in physical space to keep
taking
these exponentially increasing levels of
abstraction in intangible risk space
because it's the financial markets are
one set of instantiations but
reinsurance is an abstraction on top of
an abstraction the insurance didn't
exist in all forms forever and it keeps
getting more abstracted forward
contracts a form of insurance when
you're hedging you're doing it for
insurance speculation in markets like
that create liquidity but also are make
it noisy in terms of what the risk
profile is right so it it feels like the
when as we're drisking in abstract space
information space we have we it requires
energy that we have to burn coal for in
physical
space and so that it's it's an Insidious
problem that we continue to try to do
that but I have to go grit something at
the door but I wanted to make that point
about that relationship between climate
change and the information
space thanks one uh key Point Roland
that you you mentioned was fit fitting
The Experience Horizon to the living
beings in some ways that's the cognitive
approach which is fit it to this the
cognitive slice like the sense making
and decisions selection in the moment
and then there's the consequences for
the kinds of AI or or synthetic
intelligence models that are made for
example downloading all of the
internet's plain text Data that's more
experienced than one human life learning
and then using correlative aspects of
that large data set to then carry forth
those correlations forward that's like
the llm framework and then the question
is
how and where alongside or differently
does a small generative
model or some other kind of nested or
structured generative Model come into
play that is able to do better or
differently than just recapitulating
correlations Plus+
plus and and and how that actually plays
out and then I think there was a great
comments about how does it really get a
do opted or how does it be shown to make
a difference and it can be used in
retrospective meta
analysis possibly with the kinds of data
that you've shown today so having open
source and clear methods for doing the
retrospective and saying not saying that
that doing anything differently would
have been better but here's how this
pattern of outcomes and decision making
differed from this so give a
metaanalytic framework for longer past
time series do back casting kind of like
in stock trading and then open up that
space of well people are familiar with
stock trading and investing based upon
the mean value and this moves it into
also thinking about the variance
profiles I find this extremely
interesting as an observation so when I
used to work also at swissre together
with Stefan and I used to an initiative
in casualty and uh you see in property
uh things are somewhat objective because
you have earthquakes and you have
windstorms and they have kind of um a
physical nature and uh you you can study
how the earth works and and you
understand it uh something like
liability is much more man-made and uh
so essentially uh it's all about things
that are not supposed to happen so you
always have like an infinite
configuration space and you cannot model
it uh and already at the time it was
like 20 years ago uh but I said we we
need to have like monitors uh to
systematically scan the media what's
being published what what's the
awareness uh because with a certain
likelihood the lawyers are going to pick
up what's in the media and they are
going to do lawsuits about it which then
result in liability claims right and
there I see exact the applicability of
llms and all this stuff because what
what they can do extremely well is is
put things in a in a correlation with
each other right and and so I think
especially for modeling casualty
business I see I see a huge potential in
what you are saying so just you know
putting llms on top and and finding out
uh any any form of uh dependence between
what's being published and and lawsuits
Etc
so Stefan where are you going to go with
this work or what are your
directions
okay uh good question but you know as I
I think a briefly mentioned um this see
my have to maybe just make a short
comment about my career so I have a
degree in physics uh but then after my
PhD I then went into reinsurance
industry and I left the reinsurance
industry about 10 years ago and then I
was doing completely different things
but this topic here was kind of
something which was brewing in the back
of my mind so by exploring other fields
and the uh maybe I have to say this is
also thanks to my wife which she exposes
me to all kind of topics suddenly I got
familiar with different approach is how
to solve problems and then suddenly this
uh um I saw a way how to solve this
issue here and my intention was simply
to bring it to paper to write it down to
publish it and get it out so basically
saying okay then for me the this is done
but now Roland came into the picture and
he is now coming up with some ideas that
maybe we can do something with it so I
don't know exactly what's going to
happen I as I also mentioned I
approached some colleagues from former
colleagues but there was no big interest
and I've also seen in when I published
the paper the peer reviewers they say
yes it's interesting but for them it was
not something they say yes we need to
move in this direction it was simply
asking what is then the benefit compared
to the old approaches so so far I don't
see really
the I haven't encountered anyone which
is open to it and I didn't have any
plans because I have other ideas which I
want to presume I'm retired and I have
other projects but depending what is
happening if people approach me say yes
how can we somehow implement this
framework then I'm open to be involved
there but I have no specific plans to do
anything with it
anymore maybe some reinsurance listen to
this so I think uh uh obviously it's
it's not very nice to do it uh to do a
dry exercise with fake data uh so we
should have real data and we should have
a real interest behind it uh but maybe
if some some reinsurers are listening to
this podcast um uh please contact us and
and uh let's see that we can collaborate
in this that we can do something in
this yeah there's there's a lot of
things to say there's this
laid out
calculation and the kinds of Basi
analyses that are described with this
kind of Baseline structure and then as
you alluded to that's even before
getting into multi-agent cognitive
economics thinking more about the
decision- making the sense making of
different entities this is just taking
in a very specific approach to to
structuring the data and the
input and and it's an interesting
direction to see what what tools and how
General does the toolkit have to be like
when you say external data comes
in that could range from nothing to all
the stock data in the world so how do
you even exactly go about that to make
it useful without just saying well it
could be tiny or it could be all the
data analysis in the world and then
again how does that connect to doing
similarly or better or different than
the kinds of models already in play and
then the decisions coming out of
those I mean it's funny because oh go
ahead Stan oh sorry I think you make
your bring an interesting thought into
the picture because what I see you can
see I focus on a very tiny part of the
whole decision process but of course you
can expand now this um Market blank the
pro make say okay at the end we have
within an reur company there is many
different buckets which we could try to
understand from this uh from the
perspective of this new framework and
see how is the um the corporate decision
processes what they happening how do
different place um part parts of the
company interact how can the company
interact with there's other information
coming from the outside and you have
other stakeholders I mean I just looked
here just as the um Insurance clients
but there of course there is
the you have the financial part you have
the maybe some exchanging risk maybe you
have
the uh shareholders and so on so there
is many different facets and you can
also see them yourself as part of a
bigger economic framework and see what
is your place in there so at the end of
the day I think if you want to have kind
of digital Earth
you could try to expand this kind of
thinking into some much bigger uh
framework and and try to understand but
I don't know if anyone has the
capability to it because it sounds
pretty complex but maybe with the help
of artificial intelligence we might get
there yeah this is another thought
because every time we have these Tech
revolutions like now with the AI
Revolution uh it also shifts industry
players right so if we if we look at the
invention of the smartphone before phone
companies were called like uh Ericson or
Nokia and afterwards they were called
Apple and Google and so I think there
are always these shifts when when Tech
revolutions come and I think this this
AI Revolution together with such
modeling uh it could actually then
suddenly become attractive for big Tech
to start doing reinsurance because what
you need is you need uh Capital they
have Capital uh and and you need you
need skills and uh they are actually
quite good at you know acquiring data
and analyzing data so maybe it's exactly
this type of model that makes it
accessible for big Tech now to to enter
the
domain reinsurance on digital
information
interesting area I
mean insurance it's very simple it's B
saying we need someone who absorbs it's
the last resort for risk so you need to
be able to assess this risk and in the
case if something happens you need to be
able to pay and I mean this is the
traditional approach but this could be
easily replaced as Roland said by other
players which Step into the market and
since it's not largely regulated this
should entry point should be relatively
easy if you have the technology and if
you have also the financial strengths
behind and the of course the skills this
is the important part then you can
basically replace all the rur
industry and it's not complete fiction
if you look at Alibaba this big Chinese
um Amazon uh so Alibaba started selling
insurance so it's it's not completely
off because they they have a platform so
I could picture uh you know Amazon or or
Facebook uh to start selling insurance
it's it's it's not completely science
fiction okay very interesting uh Roland
and Scott if you have any last comments
then Stefan you can have the last word
okay all good Scott okay what if your
what's your last word
Stefan okay well I didn't think about
having a last word but I mean for me it
was very interesting also having this
discussion it was for me Al a new
experience to be in a podcast and to
present in this way I mean of course I
was presenting many uh traditionally and
it's now I'm entering it my
later days into a new uh platform which
was quite uh an interesting experience
so I enjoyed it having this conversation
and then let's see what's happening out
of
it
great all right thanks again
all till next time okay thank
you e